Pat Mitchell: Your first time back on the TEDWomen stage.
بات ميتشيل : أول عودة على المسرح في TEDWomen مجددا .
Sheryl Sandberg: First time back. Nice to see everyone. It's always so nice to look out
شيريل ساندبرغ : أول عودة لي. تسرني رؤية الجميع، من الرائع دائما أن أنظر حولي
and see so many women.
وأرى العديد من النساء.
It's so not my regular experience, as I know anyone else's.
ليست تجربة معهودة بالنسبة لي، كما هي بالنسبة لأي أحد.
PM: So when we first started talking about, maybe the subject wouldn't be social media,
ب.م : إذن عندما بدأنا نتحدث أول مرة، ربما لم يكن الحديث عن شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي،
which we assumed it would be, but that you had very much on your mind
والذي افترضنا أنه ربما يكون هو ، لكن كان هناك موضوع يشغلك كثيرا
the missing leadership positions, particularly in the sector of technology and social media.
وهو غياب وظائف القيادة، خصوصا في مجال التكنولوجيا وشبكات التواصل الاجتماعي.
But how did that evolve for you as a thought, and end up being the TED Talk that you gave?
لكين كيف تطورت هذه الفكرة لديك ، لتصبح محادثة TED تلك التي ألقيتها؟
SS: So I was really scared to get on this stage and talk about women,
كنت خائفة جدا من الوقوف على هذه المنصة والتحدث عن النساء،
because I grew up in the business world, as I think so many of us did.
لأنني كبرت في عالم الأعمال ، كما هو الحال بالنسبة للعديد منا كما أعتقد.
You never talk about being a woman, because someone might notice that you're a woman, right?
لا يمكن التحدث عن المرأة، لأنه ربما يلاحظ أحدهم أنك امرأة ،أليس كذلك؟
They might notice. Or worse, if you say "woman," people on the other end of the table
ربما يلاحظون،و الأدهى من ذلك ، حين تقولين "امرأة" يعتقد من يجلس على الطرف الآخر للطاولة
think you're asking for special treatment, or complaining.
أنك تطلبين تعاملا خاصا، أو أنك تتذمرين.
Or worse, about to sue them. And so I went through -- (Laughter)
بل أكثر من ذلك ، أنك على وشك أن تقاضيهم. وكذلك مضيت --(ضحك)
Right? I went through my entire business career,
صحيح؟ قضيت مساري المهني بأكمله،
and never spoke about being a woman, never spoke about it publicly.
دون أن أتحدث مطلقا عن كوني امرأة، لم أتحدث علنا قط عن هذا.
But I also had noticed that it wasn't working.
لكنني لاحظت أن هذا الأمر ليس صحيحا.
I came out of college over 20 years ago, and I thought
تخرجت من الجامعة منذ أكثر 20 سنة، ففكرت أن
that all of my peers were men and women, all the people above me were all men,
كل زملائي كانوا من الرجال و النساء، وكل المدراء كانوا من الرجال،
but that would change,
لكن هذا الأمر كان ليتغير،
because your generation had done such an amazing job fighting for equality,
لأن جيلكم قام بدور رائع للنضال من أجل المساواة،
equality was now ours for the taking. And it wasn't.
وقد كان علينا أن نحمل مشعل المساواة بدورنا، لكننا لم نفعل .
Because year after year, I was one of fewer and fewer,
لأنني سنة بعد سنة، كنت ضمن القلة القليلة،
and now, often the only woman in a room.
والآن ، غالبا ما أكون المرأة الوحيدة في غرفة الاجتماعات .
And I talked to a bunch of people about,
وقد تحدثت إلى مجموعة من الناس إن كان
should I give a speech at TEDWomen about women, and they said, oh no, no.
عليَّ أن ألقي محادثة في TEDWomen عن النساء، فقالوا، أوه لا، لا.
It will end your business career. You cannot be a serious business executive
ستقضين على مسارك المهني. لا يمكنك أن تكوني مديرة تنفيذية جادة
and speak about being a woman. You'll never be taken seriously again.
وتتحدثين عن كونك امرأة. لن تؤخذي على محمل الجد مطلقا مرة أخرى.
But fortunately, there were the few, the proud -- like you -- who told me I should give the speech,
لكن لحسن الحظ كان هناك أناس قليلون ، فخورون-- مثلك -- من قالوا أنه عليَّ إلقاء هذه المحادثة،
and I asked myself the question Mark Zuckerberg might --
فسألت نفسي السؤال الذي-- يطرحه مارك زكبرغ
the founder of Facebook and my boss --
مؤسس فايسبوك و مديري --
asks all of us, which is, what would I do if I wasn't afraid?
علينا جميعا، والذي كان مالذي كنت سأفعله إن لم أكن خائفا ؟
And the answer to what would I do if I wasn't afraid is I would get on the TED stage,
فكان الجواب عن السؤال مالذي كنت سأفعله إن لم أكن خائفة هو أن أعتلي منصة TED ،
and talk about women, and leadership. And I did, and survived. (Applause)
وأتحدث عن النساءوالقيادة. وقد فعلت. وها أنا ذي أمامكم.( تصفيق)
PM: I would say, not only survived. I'm thinking of that moment, Sheryl,
ب.م: لن أقول أنك فقط نجوت. كنت أفكر في تلك اللحظة، شيرل،
when you and I were standing backstage together, and you turned to me,
عندما كنت أنا و أنت خلف الكواليس معا، فالتفت نحوي،
and you told me a story.
فأخبرتني عن قصة.
And I said -- very last minute -- you know, you really should share that story.
فقلت لك --في اللحظة الأخيرة--، أتعلمين، عليك أن تروي هذه القصة حقا.
SS: Oh, yeah. PM: What was that story?
ش س: أوه، أجل ب.م : ما هي تلك القصة؟
SS: Well, it's an important part of the journey. So I had -- TEDWomen --
ش س : حسنا، إنها جزء مهم من الرحلة. كان هناك مؤتمر-- TEDWomen --
the original one was in D.C. -- so I live here, so I had gotten on a plane the day before,
المؤتمر الأساسي كان في واشنطن دي سي-- وأنا كنت أعيش هنا، وكان عليَّ أن آخذ الطائرة في اليوم السابق،
and my daughter was three, she was clinging to my leg: "Mommy, don't go."
كانت ابنتي تبلغ الثالثة من العمر، وكانت تشدني من قدمي و تقول : "ماما لا تذهبي ."
And Pat's a friend, and so, not related to the speech I was planning on giving,
وبما أنني صديقة بام، وما إلى ذلك، وكان الأمر لا يتعلق بمحادثتي التي كنت أنوي إلقاءها،
which was chock full of facts and figures, and nothing personal,
والتي كانت مليئة بالوقائع و الأرقام ، ولم تكن تحمل شيئا شخصيا ،
I told Pat the story. I said, well, I'm having a hard day.
أخبرت بام عن القصة. و قلت ، حسنا ، أنا أمر بيوم صعب جدا.
Yesterday my daughter was clinging to my leg, and "Don't go."
تعلقت ابنتي البارحة بقدمي ،و قالت لي "لاتذهبي."
And you looked at me and said, you have to tell that story.
فنظرتِ إليَّ، وقلتَ لي : عليك أن تروي هذه القصة.
I said, on the TED stage? Are you kidding?
فقلتُ : على مسرح TED؟ هل تمزحين ؟
I'm going to get on a stage and admit my daughter was clinging to my leg?
هل أصعد على المسرح وأعترف أن ابنتي تعلقت بقدمي ؟
And you said yes, because if you want to talk about getting more women into leadership roles,
فقلتِ لي نعم ،لأنك إن كنت تريدين أن تتحدثي عن حصول النساء على مزيد من مناصب القيادة ،
you have to be honest about how hard it is.
عليك أن تكوني صادقة عن مدى صعوبة ذلك .
And I did. And I think that's a really important part of the journey.
وكذلك فعلت.وأعتقد أن هذا الأمر كان مهما في مساري.
The same thing happened when I wrote my book. I started writing the book. I wrote a first chapter,
نفس الشيء حدث حينما كنت أكتب كتابي. بدأت في الكتاب، كتبت الفصل الأول،
I thought it was fabulous. It was chock-full of data and figures,
كنت أعتقد أنه مذهل، كان مليئا بالبيانات و الأرقام
I had three pages on matrilineal Maasai tribes, and their sociological patterns.
كانت هناك ثلاث صفحات عن قبائل الماساي وعن أنماطهم الإجتماعية.
My husband read it and he was like, this is like eating your Wheaties. (Laughter)
نظر زوجي إلى هذا فقال : أوه، الأمر أشبه بأكل رقائق ويتيز .(ضحك)
No one -- and I apologize to Wheaties if there's someone -- no one, no one will read this book.
لا أحد --وأعتذرإن كان أي ممثل عن ويتيز هنا -- لاأحد ، لاأحد سيقرأ هذا الكتاب.
And I realized through the process that I had to be more honest and more open,
أدركت من خلال العمل ، أنه يجب علي أن أكون أكثر صدقا و أكثر انفتاحا،
and I had to tell my stories. My stories of still not feeling as self-confident as I should,
وأنه علي أن أروي قصصي. قصصي عن أنني لست واثقة بنفسي كما يجب ،
in many situations. My first and failed marriage. Crying at work.
في العديد من الحالات،عن زواجي الأول الفاشل. عن بكائي في العمل.
Felling like I didn't belong there, feeling guilty to this day.
شعوري أنه لم أكن أنتمي إلى ذلك المكان، شعوري بالذنب إلى اليوم .
And part of my journey, starting on this stage, going to "Lean In," going to the foundation,
وكجزء من رحلتي ، ابتداء ا بوقوفي على هذا المسرح، مرورا بكتابي "لين إن"، وصولا إلى المؤسسة التي أسستها،
is all about being more open and honest about those challenges,
فالأمر يتعلق بأن نكون أكثر انفتاحا و أكثر صدقا اتجاه هذه التحديات،
so that other women can be more open and honest,
لكي تكون النساء الأخريات أكثر انفتاحا و أكثر صدقا ،
and all of us can work together towards real equality.
ولكي نستطيع العمل جميعا لتحقيق مساواة حقيقية.
PM: I think that one of the most striking parts about the book,
ب م : أعتقد أن هذا أحد الأجزاء اللافتة للنظر فيما يخص الكتاب،
and in my opinion, one of the reasons it's hit such a nerve and is resonating around the world,
و في اعتقادي، هذا ما جعله يصيب عصبا حساسا ، و يحدث كل هذا الصدى في جميع أنحاء العالم،
is that you are personal in the book, and that you do make it clear that,
أنه كنت تتحدثين عنكِ أنتِ في هذا الكتاب،وقد أوضحتِ أنك
while you've observed some things that are very important for other women to know,
بينما كنت تلاحظين مجموعة من الأمور التي من المهم أن تعلمها النساء الأخريات،
that you've had the same challenges that many others of us have,
كنت أيضا تواجهين نفس التحديات التي تواجهها العديد منا ،
as you faced the hurdles and the barriers and possibly the people who don't believe the same.
حيث واجهتِ العوائق و المصاعب ، ومن الممكن أيضا، واجهت أناسا لم يؤمنوا بما تقومين به.
So talk about that process: deciding you'd go public with the private part,
أخبرينا عن المسار : كيف قررت أن تَخْرُجي إلى العلن بأجزاء خاصة،
and then you would also put yourself in the position of something of an expert
وأن تضعي أيضا نفسك في موقع الخبيرة أيضا
on how to resolve those challenges.
في كيفية حل هذه التحديات.
SS: After I did the TED Talk, what happened was --
ش س : بعدما قمت بمحادثة TED ماحدث أنه--
you know, I never really expected to write a book, I'm not an author, I'm not a writer,
أتدرين ، لم أتوقع قط أن ألف كتابا، لست مؤلفة، لست كاتبة
and it was viewed a lot, and it really started impacting people's lives.
لقد شوهدت المحادثة بكثرة، وقد بدأ فعلا في التأثير في حياة الناس .
I got this great --- one of the first letters I got was from a woman
وتوصلت بتلك الرسائل الرائعة-- إحدى الرسائل الأولى توصلت بها من امرأة
who said that she was offered a really big promotion at work, and she turned it down,
قالت أنها حصلت على ترقية مهمة في العمل، لكنها رفضتها،
and she told her best friend she turned it down, and her best friend said,
فأخبرت صديقتها المفضلة أنها رفضت هذه الترقية، فقالت لها صديقتها،
you really need to watch this TED Talk.
عليك حقا أن تشاهدي محادثة TED هذه.
And so she watched this TED Talk, and she went back the next day, she took the job,
فشاهدت محادثة TED، فعادت في اليوم الموالي ، فوافقت على العمل،
she went home, and she handed her husband the grocery list. (Laughter)
عادت إلى البيت ، وأعطت زوجها لائحة المشتريات اللازمة من البقالة .(ضحك)
And she said, I can do this.
وقالت. أستطيع القيام بهذا.
And what really mattered to me -- it wasn't only women in the corporate world,
وماكان يهمني حقا-- ليس فقط النساء اللاتي يعملن في الشركات الكبرى،
even though I did hear from a lot of them, and it did impact a lot of them,
رغم أنني سمعت منهن أيضا، وأثرت في الكثيرات منهن،
it was also people of all different circumstances.
بل كان الناس من مختلف الحالات و الظروف.
There was a doctor I met who was an attending physician at Johns Hopkins,
التقيت دكتورا ، كان طبيبا محاضرا في جونز هوبكينز،
and he said that until he saw my TED Talk, it never really occurred to him
وقال أنه قبل أن يشاهد محادثتي في TED، لم يخطر بباله قط
that even though half the students in his med school classes were women,
أنه وإن كان نصف طلاب كلية الطب من النساء ،
they weren't speaking as much as the men as he did his rounds.
لم يكن يتحدثن بقدر ما كان يتحدث الطلاب حين كان يقوم بجولاته.
So he started paying attention, and as he waited for raised hands, he realized the men's hands were up.
فبدأ يعير الانتباه، وينتظر ليرى من سيرفع يده، فلاحظ أن الطلاب الذكور من كانوا يرفعون أيديهم.
So he started encouraging the women to raise their hands more,
فبدأ بتشجيع الطالبات برفع أيديهن أكثر،
and it still didn't work.
لكن ذلك لم ينجح.
So he told everyone, no more hand raising, I'm cold-calling.
فقال للجميع، لا رفع للأيادي بعد اليوم، سأنادي من سيجيب.
So he could call evenly on men and women. And what he proved to himself was that
فكان ينادي الطلاب و الطالبات بشكل متساو. وما أثبته لنفسه كان
the women knew the answers just as well or better,
أن الطالبات كن يعرفن الإجابة بشكل متساو أو أفضل من الطلاب،
and he was able to go back to them and tell them that.
وكان بمقدوره أن يعود إليهن و يخبرهن بذلك.
And then there was the woman, stay-at-home mom, lives in a really difficult neighborhood,
بعدها كانت هناك سيدة، ربة بيت، تعيش في حي فقير جدا ،
with not a great school, she said that TED Talk -- she's never had a corporate job,
ليست ذات تعليم عال ، قالت أن محادثة TED -- لم تعمل قط بشركة كبرى،
but that TED Talk inspired her to go to her school and fight for a better teacher for her child.
لكن محادثة TED تلك ألهمتها أن تذهب إلى مدرسة الحي ، وتناضل من أجل أن يكون لابنها معلم أفضل.
And I guess it was part of was finding my own voice.
وأعتقد أن جزء ا من هذا كان أن وجدت صوتي في ما قلن.
And I realized that other women and men could find their voice through it,
وأدركت أن نساء ا ورجالا كثرا سيجدون أصواتهم من خلاله ،
which is why I went from the talk to the book.
ولهذا السبب انتقلت من المحادثة إلى الكتاب.
PM: And in the book, you not only found your voice, which is clear and strong in the book,
ب م : و في الكتاب لا نجد فقط صوتك، والذي كان قويا و واضحا فيه،
but you also share what you've learned --
لكن أيضا تقاسمت مع الناس ما تعلمته --
the experiences of other people in the lessons.
تجارب الناس الآخرين و الدروس.
And that's what I'm thinking about in terms of putting yourself in a --
وماكنت أفكر فيه هو أنك وضعت نفسك في--
you became a sort of expert in how you lean in.
قد أصبحت خبيرة فيما عشته.
So what did that feel like, and become like in your life?
مالذي تشعرين به حيال هذا الأمر، ومالذي أصبح يشكله في حياتك ؟
To launch not just a book, not just a best-selling, best-viewed talk,
ليس فقط إصدار كتاب أصبح الأكثر مبيعا، أو المحادثة الأكثر مشاهدة،
but a movement, where people began to literally describe their actions at work as,
بل حراكا، حيث أصبح الناس يصفون بدقة تصرفاتهم في العمل على أنها،
I'm leaning in.
نوع من التأقلم.
SS: I mean, I'm grateful, I'm honored, I'm happy, and it's the very beginning.
ش س : أنا ممتنة، لي الشرف ، وأنا سعيدة، هذه فقط البداية الأولى.
So I don't know if I'm an expert, or if anyone is an expert. I certainly have done a lot of research.
لذلك فأنا لا أعتقد أنني خبيرة ، أو أن هناك من يمتلك الخبرة، قمت بالتأكيد بالعديد من الأبحاث.
I have read every study, I have pored over the materials,
قرأت كل الدراسات، انكببت على دراسة المواد،
and the lessons are very clear. Because here's what we know:
واضحة جدا،إليكم ما نعلمه:
What we know is that stereotypes are holding women back from leadership roles all over the world.
مانعلمه أن الصور النمطية تحول دون وصول النساء إلى مناصب القيادة في جميع أنحاء العالم.
It's so striking. "Lean In" is very global, I've been all over the world,
إنه أمر مدهش،" " هو مصطلح عالمي ، وهو أمر يحدث في جميع أنحاء العالم،
talking about it, and -- cultures are so different.
والحديث يدور حوله و-- رغم أن الثقافات مختلفة جدا.
Even within our own country, to Japan, to Korea, to China, to Asia, Europe,
حتى في بلدنا، إلى اليابان، كوريا ، إلى الصين، إلى آسيا ، أوروبا،
they're so different. Except for one thing: gender.
كلها بلدان مختلفة، باستثناء أمر واحد : النوع .
All over the world, no matter what our cultures are,
في جميع أنحاء العالم، مهما كانت ثقافاتنا،
we think men should be strong, assertive, aggressive, have voice;
نعتقد أنه على الرجال أن يكونوا أقوياء، مواظبين، مكافحين، لهم حضور،
we think women should speak when spoken to, help others.
وأن على النساء أن يتحدثن إذا وُجَّهَ لهن الكلام ، وأن يساعدن الآخرين.
Now we have, all over the world,
نسمع الآن ، في جميع أنحاء العالم،
women are called "bossy." There is a word for "bossy,"
أن النساء يلَقَّبن ب " المتسلطات". هناك كلمة "متسلطة"،
for little girls, in every language there's one.
تطلق على الفتيات الصغيرات ، في كل اللغات توجد كلمة بهذا المعنى.
It's a word that's pretty much not used for little boys,
وهي كلمة لا تستعمل كثيرا لوصف الأولاد الصغار،
because if a little boy leads, there's no negative word for it,
لأن الولد الصغير إذا قاد، لاتوجد كلمة سلبية لوصفه،
it's expected. But if a little girl leads, she's bossy.
إذ أن الأمر متوقع. لكن إذا قادت الفتاة، فهي متسلطة.
Now I know there aren't a lot of men here, but bear with me.
أعلم أنه ليس هناك العديد من الرجال الحاضرين هنا، ولكن أرجو أن تتحملوني.
If you're a man, you'll have to represent your gender.
إن كنت رجلا، فعليك أن تمثل جنسك.
Please raise your hand if you've been told you're too aggressive at work.
رجاء ا ارفعوا أيديكم إن كان قد قيل لكم مرة أنكم عدوانيون في العمل.
(Laughter) There's always a few, it runs about five percent. Okay, get ready, gentlemen.
(ضحك) هناك دائما عدد محدود ، حوالي 5%. حسنا ،استعدوا يا سادة.
If you're a woman, please raise your hand if you've ever been told you're too aggressive at work.
إن كنت امرأة، رجاء ا ارفعي يدك إن كان قد قيل لك أنك عدوانية جدا في العمل.
(Laughter) That is what audiences have said in every country in the world,
(ضحك)هذا ما يقوله الحضور في جميع أنحاء العالم ،
and it's deeply supported by the data.
و الأمر مدعوم جدا بالبيانات.
Now, do we think women are more aggressive than men? Of course not.
الآن، هل نعتقد فعلا أن النساء عدوانيات أكثر من الرجال؟ بالطبع لا.
It's just that we judge them through a different lens,
نحن فقط نحكم عليهن من خلال عدسة مختلفة،
and a lot of the character traits that you must exhibit to perform at work, to get results, to lead,
فالعديد من السمات الشخصية التي عليك إظهارها ،لإنجاز العمل، وتحقيق النتائج، وللقيادة،
are ones that we think, in a man, he's a boss,
هي تلك التي نعتقد أنها تجعل من الرجل ، رئيسا للعمل،
and in a woman, she's bossy.
ومن المرأة ،امرأة متسلطة.
And the good news about this is that we can change this by acknowledging it.
والخبر السار حيال هذا الأمر أننا نستطيع تغييره من خلال الاعتراف به.
One of the happiest moments I had in this whole journey is,
إحدى اللحظات السعيدة التي حظيت بها خلال هاته الرحلة برمتها،
after the book came out, I stood on a stage with John Chambers, the CEO of Cisco.
بعد صدور الكتاب، وقفت على المسرح مع جون تشامبرز، الرئيس التنفيذي لشركة سيسكو.
He read the book. He stood on a stage with me, he invited me in front of his whole management team,
كان قد قرأ الكتاب. وقف معي على المسرح، ودعاني أمام كل فريقه الاداري،
men and women, and he said, I thought we were good at this. I thought I was good at this.
رجالا و نساء ، وقال كنت أعتقد أننا كنا نبلي بلاءا حسنا، كنت أعتقد أنني أبلي بلاءا حسنا.
And then I read this book, and I realized that we -- my company --
بعدها قرأت هذا الكتاب ،وأدركت أننا-- شركتي --
we have called all of our senior women too aggressive,
كنا نلقب كل مديراتنا بالعدوانيات،
and I'm standing on this stage, and I'm sorry.
وأنا أقف على هذا المسرح ،لأقول لكن أنا آسف.
And I want you to know we're never going to do it again.
وأريدكن أن تعلمن أننا لن نفعل هذا مجددا أبدا.
PM: Can we send that to a lot of other people that we know? (Applause)
ب م : هل يمكننا أن نرسل هذه الرسالة للكثير من الناس الذين نعرفهم؟ (تصفيق)
SS: And so John is doing that because he believes it's good for his company,
ش س : قام جون بهذا لأنه يؤمن بأنه أمر جيد بالنسبة لشركته،
and so this kind of acknowledgement of these biases can change it.
وبالتالي بإمكان هذا النوع من الاعتراف بهذه الأخطاء أن يغير الأمر.
And so next time you all see someone call a little girl "bossy,"
ففي المرة القادمة ، حين ترى شخصا ينعت صغيرته" بالمتسلطة"،
you walk right up to that person, big smile, and you say,
اتجه نحوه ، وبابتسامة عريضة، قل له،
"That little girl's not bossy. That little girl has executive leadership skills." (Laughter)
"هذه الطفلة الصغيرة ليست متسلطة. هذه الطفلة الصغيرة تملك مهارات القيادة التنفيذية. (ضحك)"
PM: I know that's what you're telling your daughter. SS: Absolutely.
ب م : أعلم أن هذا ما تقولينه لابنتك . ش س : بالتأكيد.
PM: And you did focus in the book -- and the reason, as you said, in writing it,
ب م : و لقد ركزت في الكتاب و السبب كما قلت في كتابته ،
was to create a dialogue about this.
هو خلق حوار حول هذا الموضوع.
I mean, let's just put it out there, face the fact that women are --
أعني ، لنطرح الأمر على الشكل التالي، لنواجه واقع النساء اللاتي --
in a time when we have more open doors, and more opportunities --
في الوقت الذي توجد فيه العديد من الأبواب المفتوحة و الفرص المتاحة--
are still not getting to the leadership positions.
اللاتي لم يحصلن بعد على فرص القيادة في العمل.
So in the months that have come since the book,
في الشهور التي تلت إصدار الكتاب،
in which "Lean In" focused on that and said,
الذي ركز على وتحدث عن مفهوم "التأقلم" ،
here are some of the challenges that remain, and many of them we have to own within ourselves
هناك بعض التحديات التي لا زالت تواجهنا، و العديد منها لازال من الواجب علينا حملها
and look at ourselves. What has changed?
وننظر بداخلنا ونتساءل، مالذي تغير؟
Have you seen changes?
هل رأيت تغيرا ما؟
SS: Well, there's certainly more dialogue, which is great.
ش س : هناك بالتأكيد حوار مستمر، وهذا أمر رائع.
But what really matters to me, and I think all of us, is action.
لكن مايهمني حقا، و أعتقد أنه يهمنا جميعا، هو التحرك و القيام بأمر ما.
So everywhere I go, CEOs, they're mostly men, say to me,
حيثما ذهبت يخاطبني المدراء التنفيذيون، و معظمهم من الرجال، قائلين،
you're costing me so much money
أنتن تكلفن الكثير من المال
because all the women want to be paid as much as the men.
لأن النساء يردن أن يتقاضين أجورا متساوية مع الرجال.
And to them I say, I'm not sorry at all. (Laughter)
فأجيبهم قائلة : حسنا ،لست آسفة على الإطلاق.( ضحك)
At all. I mean, the women should be paid as much as the men.
على الإطلاق ،على النساء أن يتقاضين أجورا متساوية مع الرجال.
Everywhere I go, women tell me they ask for raises.
حيثما ذهبت، تخبرني النساء أنهن يطالبن برفع رواتبهن.
Everywhere I go, women say they're getting better relationships with their spouses,
حيثما ذهبت، تخبرني النساء أن علاقاتهن مع أزواجهن صارت أفضل،
asking for more help at home, asking for the promotions they should be getting at work,
يطلبن المساعدة في المنزل، يطلبن الترقيات التي يجب أن يحصلن عليها في العمل ،
and importantly, believing it themselves. Even little things.
والأهم من هذا كله، أنهن يؤمنَّ بهذا بأنفسهن. حتى وإن كانت الأمور صغيرة.
One of the governors of one of the states told me that he didn't realize that more women were, in fact,
أخبرني أحد حكام إحدى الولايات أنه لم يكن يدرك أنه بالفعل ،كانت هناك العديد من النساء،
literally sitting on the side of the room, which they are,
يجلسن في أركان الغرفة، وكن فعلا كذلك،
and now he made a rule that all the women on his staff need to sit at the table.
لكنه وضع الآن قاعدة أنه على جميع النساء في فريقه أن تنضم إلى الطاولة.
The foundation I started along with the book "Lean In"
فالمؤسسة التي أسستها بالتزامن مع كتابي "لين إين"
helps women, or men, start circles -- small groups,
تساعد النساء ، أو الرجال ، أن يبدؤوا بحلقات-- مجموعات صغيرة،
it can be 10, it can be however many you want, which meet once a month.
لعشرة أشخاص مثلا، أو أيا كان عدد أفرادها، يلتقون مرة كل شهر.
I would have hoped that by now, we'd have about 500 circles. That would've been great.
كنت آمل أن تكون لدينا 500 حلقة، كان الأمر ليكون رائعا.
You know, 500 times roughly 10.
500 ضرب 10، تقريبا.
There are over 12,000 circles in 50 countries in the world.
لدينا أكثر من 12000 حلقة في 50 دولة في العالم.
PM: Wow, that's amazing.
ب.م : واو؛ هذا مدهش.
SS: And these are people who are meeting every single month.
ش.س :يلتقي هؤلاء الناس بشكل منتظم كل شهر.
I met one of them, I was in Beijing.
التقيت بعضهم، كنت في بكين ،
A group of women, they're all about 29 or 30, they started the first Lean In circle in Beijing,
مجموعة من النساء، أعمارهن حوالي 29 أو 30 عاما، كن قد بدأن أول حلقة في بكين ،
several of them grew up in very poor, rural China.
أغلبهن ترعرعن في قرى الصين الفقيرة.
These women are 29, they are told by their society that they are "left over,"
كن نساء في 29 من عمرهن، يرسل لهن المجتمع رسالة مفادهنا أنهن "متخلى عنهن،"
because they are not yet married,
لأنهن لم يتزوجن بعد،
and the process of coming together once a month at a meeting
و لقاؤهن مع بعضهن البعض مرة كل شهر
is helping them define who they are for themselves.
يساعدهن على التعرف على هويتهن بأنفسهن.
What they want in their careers. The kind of partners they want, if at all.
ماذا يردن في مسارهن المهني، مانوع الأزواج اللاتي يردن، إن قررن الزواج.
I looked at them, we went around and introduced ourselves,
نظرت إليهن، عرفنا بأنفسنا ،
and they all said their names and where they're from,
فعرفن بأسمائهن و من أين جئن،
and I said, I'm Sheryl Sandberg, and this was my dream.
فقلت أنا اسمي شيريل ساندبورغ، وهذا كان حلمي.
And I kind of just started crying.
فبدأت أبكي.
Right, which, I admit, I do. Right? I've talked about it before.
صحيح، أعترف بذلك، صحيح؟ تحدثت عن هذا الأمر من قبل.
But the fact that a woman so far away out in the world, who grew up in a rural village,
لكن أمرا من قبيل أن امرأة في مكان ما بعيد جدا نشأت في قرية،
who's being told to marry someone she doesn't want to marry,
والتي ُيطلب منها أن تتزوج شخصا لا تريد الزواج منه،
can now go meet once a month with a group of people and refuse that,
تستطيع الآن أن تلتقي مرة كل شهر بمجموعة من الأشخاص وترفض هذا الأمر،
and find life on her own terms.
وتجد حياة هي من ترسم معالمها.
That's the kind of change we have to hope for.
هذا هو التغيير الذي كنا نأمله.
PM: Have you been surprised by the global nature of the message?
ب.م: هل تفاجأتي بأن أصبحت رسالتك ذات طابع عالمي ؟
Because I think when the book first came out, many people thought,
لأنني أعتقد أنه عندما صدر الكتاب، اعتقد الناس ،
well, this is a really important handbook for young women on their way up.
حسنا ، هذا كتاب عملي مهم جدا بالنسبة للنساء الشابات اللاتي يحاولن شق طريقهن نحو النجاح.
They need to look at this, anticipate the barriers, and recognize them,
عليهن أن يطلعن عليه، يتوقعن العراقيل، يتعرفن عليها،
put them out in the open, have the dialogue about it,
يتحدثن عنها بانفتاح، ويتحاورن حولها،
but that it's really for women who are that. Doing that. Pursuing the corporate world.
لكن هذا كان موجها لهذه الفئة من النساء.من يقمن بهذا، من يسلكن مسارهن المهني في عالم الشركات الكبرى.
And yet the book is being read, as you say, in rural and developing countries.
لكن بالمقابل تمت قراءة الكتاب، كما قلت، في القرى والدول النامية ،
What part of that has surprised you, and perhaps led to a new perspective on your part?
ما الجانب الذي كان مفاجئا بالنسبة لك، والذي ربما دفعك نحو أبعاد جديدة ؟
SS: The book is about self-confidence, and about equality.
ش.س : يتحدث الكتاب عن الثقة في النفس و عن المساواة.
And it turns out, everywhere in the world, women need more self-confidence,
وقد تبين ، أن النساء في جميع أنحاء العالم يحتجن إلى المزيد من الثقة في النفس،
because the world tells us we're not equal to men.
لأن العالم يقول لنا إننا لسنا متساويات مع الرجال.
Everywhere in the world, we live in a world where the men get "and,"
في كل مكان في العالم ، يحصل الرجال على أشياء "و" أخرى،
and women get "or."
بينما تحصل النساء على أشياء "أو" أخرى.
I've never met a man who's been asked how he does it all. (Laughter)
لم ألتق رجلا قط وقد سُئِلَ : كيف كان بإمكانه أن يقوم بعدة أشياء في آن واحد. (ضحك)
Again, I'm going to turn to the men in the audience:
مرة أخرى، سأتوجه بالسؤال للحضور من الرجال:
Please raise your hand if you've been asked, how do you do it all?
ارفعوا أيديكم من فضلكم ،إن كنتم قد سُئِلتم كيف يمكنكم القيام بعدة أشياء في آن واحد؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Men only.
الرجال فقط.
Women, women. Please raise your hand if you've been asked how you do it all?
النساء، النساء.من فضلكن ، ارفعن أيديكن إن كنت قد سئلتن من قبل كيف يمكنكن القيام بعدة أشياء في آن واحد؟
We assume men can do it all, slash -- have jobs and children.
نفترض أن الرجال يمكنهم القيام بكل شيء، يعني-- ان لديهم عمل و أطفال.
We assume women can't, and that's ridiculous,
و نفترض أن النساء لا يمكنهن ذلك ، وهذا أمر سخيف،
because the great majority of women everywhere in the world, including the United States,
لأن الغالبية العظمى من النساء في كل أنحاء العالم ، بما في ذلك في الولايات المتحدة،
work full time and have children.
يعملن بدوام كامل ، ولديهن أطفال.
And I think people don't fully understand how broad the message is.
ولأ أعتقد أن الناس يعون مدى سعة هذه الرسالة.
There is a circle that's been started for rescued sex workers in Miami.
هناك حلقة قد بدأت في ميامي لمساعدة ممتهني الجنس.
They're using "Lean In" to help people make the transition
يستعملون مفهوم " تأقلم" لمساعدة الناس على اجتياز مرحلة التحول
back to what would be a fair life, really rescuing them from their pimps, and using it.
والعودة إلى مايمكنها أن تكون حياة كريمة، فعلا إنقاذهم من الدعارة.
There are dress-for-success groups in Texas which are using the book,
هناك حلقات "لباس للنجاح"، في تكساس والتي تستعمل الكتاب،
for women who have never been to college.
لمساعدة النساء التي لم يدرسن قط بالجامعة.
And we know there are groups all the way to Ethiopia.
ونعلم أن هناك مجموعات ، هناك بعيدا في أثيوبيا.
And so these messages of equality -- of how women are told they can't have what men can have --
إذن فهذه رسائل مساواة-- كيف كان يقال للنساء أنهن لا يمكنهن الحصول على ما يمكن للرجال الحصول عليه--
how we assume that leadership is for men, how we assume that voice is for men,
وكيف نفترض أن القيادة هي فقط للرجال، وأن القول الفصل للرجال،
these affect all of us, and I think they are very universal.
وهذا يؤثر فينا جميعا، وأعتقد أن هذه الأمور متعارف عليها عالميا.
And it's part of what TEDWomen does.
وهذا جزء مما يقوم به مؤتمر TEDWomen.
It unites all of us in a cause we have to believe in,
فهو يجمعنا حول قضية علينا الإيمان بها،
which is more women, more voice, more equality.
وهي نساء قائدات أكثر، صوت مسموع أقوى ،و مساواة أكبر.
PM: If you were invited now to make another TEDWomen talk,
ب.م : لو دُعيتِ الآن لتلقي محادثة أخرى في TEDWomen،
what would you say that is a result of this experience, for you personally,
ماذا يمكنك أن تطلعينا عليه كخلاصة لتجربتك، بالنسبة لك شخصيا،
and what you've learned about women, and men,
وماذا تعلمته عن النساء و الرجال،
as you've made this journey?
وأنت تخوضين هذه الرحلة؟
SS: I think I would say -- I tried to say this strongly,
ش.س :أعتقد أنني كنت لأقول-- حاولت قول هذا بشكل أقوى،
but I think I can say it more strongly --
لكنني أعتقد أنه بإمكاني أن أقول هذا بقوة أكبر--
I want to say that the status quo is not enough.
أعتقد أن الوضع الراهن ليس كافيا.
That it's not good enough, that it's not changing quickly enough.
ليس جيدا بما فيه الكفاية ، وأنه لا يغير الأمر بشكل أسرع بما يكفي.
Since I gave my TED Talk and published my book, another year of data came out from the U.S. Census.
منذ أن ألقيت محادثة TED و نشرت كتابي، صدرت دراسة سنوية جديدة عن مركز الإحصاء الامريكي.
And you know what we found?
هل تعلمون ماذا وجدنا؟
No movement in the wage gap for women in the United States.
لم يُسَجَّل أي تحرك في فارق رواتب النساء في الولايات المتحدة.
Seventy-seven cents to the dollar.
77 سنتا للدولار.
If you are a black woman, 64 cents.
إن كنت امرأة سمراء ، 65 سنتا.
If you are a Latina, we're at 54 cents.
إن كنت لاتينية لك 54 سنتا.
Do you know when the last time those numbers went up?
هل تعلمون متى كانت آخر مرة ارتفعت فيها هذه الأرقام ؟
2002.
2002.
We are stagnating, we are stagnating in so many ways.
نحن لا نحرز تقدما، وهذا في عدة اتجاهات.
And I think we are not really being honest about that,
وأعتقد أننا لسنا صرحاء جدا فيما يخص هذا الأمر ،
for so many reasons. It's so hard to talk about gender.
وذلك لعدة أسباب. من الصعب جدا التحدث عن النوع.
We shy away from the word "feminist," a word I really think we need to embrace.
لأننا نخجل من مصطلح" مناصرة لقضايا المرأة" مصطلح أعتقد أن علينا أن نعتنقه.
We have to get rid of the word bossy and bring back --
علينا أن نتخلص من مصطلح " متسلطة" ونعيد--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I think I would say in a louder voice, we need to get rid of the word "bossy"
أعتقد أن علي أن أقول هذا بصوت أعلى، علينا أن نتخلص من مصطلح " متسلطة"
and bring back the word "feminist," because we need it.
نعيد مصطلح "مناصرة لقضايا المرأة " لأننا نحتاجه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: And we all need to do a lot more leaning in.
ب.م : وعلينا أن نتأقلم أكثر.
SS: A lot more leaning in.
ش.س :الكثير من التأقلم
PM: Thank you, Sheryl.
ب.م : شكرا لك شيريل
Thanks for leaning in and saying yes.
شكرا لأنك تأقلمت وأنك قلت نعم.
SS: Thank you.
ش.س : شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)